Patrick Pinnell Collection
Hartford History Center, Hartford Public Library
Patrick Pinnell Collection
1997-2001
Hartford History Center, Hartford Public Library Hartford, Connecticut
Pinnell, Patrick
4.75 linear feet
Correspondence and documentation relating to urban renewal, transportation, and parking in downtown Hartford at the end of the twentieth century.
Historical Note
Patrick Pinnell is an architect, planner, author and architectural educator, with an office in Higganum, Connecticut. Pinnell taught at Yale from 1981 to 1998. Before moving to Connecticut in 1989, his practice was based in Washington, D.C. After moving to Connecticut, he was involved in various Hartford-area planning projects, including Adriaen’s Landing, the Civic Center Revitalization Project, Rentschler Field, Riverfront Recapture, the Trinity College Master Plan and various redevelopment proposals for downtown Hartford. He also served on the Hartford Parking Authority and worked on a regional transit strategy with the Hartford Downtown Council’s Community Advisory Group. He donated the Patrick Pinnell Collection to the Hartford History Center in 2010.
Scope and Content
The Patrick Pinnell Collection includes team logs and drafts for various planning efforts in the Hartford area, and copies of communications between team members including Antonio Gomez-Palacio, Ken Greenberg, Nicola Jansco, Walter Kulash and Warren Price; reports issued by various architectural firms and agencies, photographs; and maps of sites in Hartford. The collection also includes a significant mass of clippings both from Hartford area newspapers and magazines and from newspapers from other cities relating to redevelopment in Hartford. These clippings were shared and saved and influenced the team’s planning process.
Access Restrictions
The records are stored in a restricted area and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
Accruals
The collection is closed. Additional accruals are not expected.
Subject Headings
Personal Names
Gomez-Palacio, Antonio; Greenberg, Ken; Jansco, Nicola; Kulash, Walter; Pinnell, Patrick; Price, Warren
Corporate Names
Adriaen’s Landing (Hartford, Conn.); Civic Center (Hartford, Conn.); Hartford Parking Authority; Horace Bushnell Memorial Hall (Hartford, Conn.); Rentschler Field (East Hartford, Conn.); Trinity College (Hartford, Conn.); United Technologies Corporation
Subjects
Gardens; Highways; Local transit; Parking garages; Transportation; Urban renewal
Geographic names
Asylum Street (Hartford, Conn.); East Hartford (Conn.); Lewis Street (Hartford, Conn.); Morgan Street (Hartford, Conn.); Park Street (Hartford, Conn.); Pearl Street (Hartford, Conn.); Trumbull Street (Hartford, Conn.)
Genre Terms
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence; Maps; Photographs
Contents:
- Items
  - Bushnell expansion, 1998; Program (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bushnell expansion, 1998; Design illustrations (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bushnell expansion, 1998; Interim presentation by Wilson Butler Lodge, Inc. and Schoenhardt Architects (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bushnell expansion, 1998-1999; Clippings and correspondence (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Butler-McCook homestead, 1997; Competition for design of Alexander A. Goldfarb Memorial Gate. Includes call to Artists/Designers, press release, plan of garden, article from Northeast Magazine (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Civic Center, 1998; Redevelopment opportunities (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Civic Center, 1998; Request for qualifications/proposal (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Civic Center Revitalization Project, 1998; Correspondence, plans, photographs (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Civic Center/Cutter site/410 Asylum/Society Block, 1998; Description of redevelopment opportunities prepared by Urban Strategies, Inc., Svigals Associates, and Patrick Pinnell (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Civic Center/Cutter site/410 Asylum/Society Block, 1998; Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Civic Center/Cutter site/410 Asylum/Society Block, 1998; Miscellaneous memos, proposals, sketches (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Cutter site, 1997-1998; Business cards, photographs of Lewis Street, Pearl Street with notes of dates when some buildings were constructed (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Cutter site, 1997-1998; Maps, notes, and newspaper clippings about Lewis Street, Pearl Street, Trumbull Street (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Cutter site, 1997; Dowling & Partners securities proposal (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Cutter site, 1997; Proposal (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Cutter site, 1997; Draft proposal (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Cutter site, 1997; Proposals (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Cutter site, 1997; Hennessey Company proposal (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Cutter site, 1997; Lewis Street Partners proposal (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Cutter site, 1997; Value Realty Partners proposal (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Cutter site, 1997; Proposal from Lewis & Pearl Connection, LLC submitted by Thompson Gould Page, attorney at law (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Cutter site, 1997; Proposal from Lewis & Pearl Connection, LLC submitted by Thompson Gould Page, attorney at law (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 410 Asylum/370 Asylum, 1998-1999; Correspondence, plans, proposals for Capitol Building and former Garde Hotel building (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 410 Asylum/370 Asylum, 1998-1999; Notes and proposal (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 410 Asylum, 1998-1999; Proposal (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 410 Asylum, 1998-1999; Redevelopment opportunities (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 410 Asylum, 1998-1999; Business cards and photographs of Asylum Street (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Society site, 1998; Business cards and photographs of Main Street, Asylum Street and surrounding area (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Society site, 1998; Draft proposal for site at the corner of Main and Asylum Streets named for the former Society of Savings (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Society site, 1998; Notes and annotated proposal (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Society site, 1998; Redevelopment opportunities (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Society site, 1998; Plans, proposals, newspaper clippings and other documentation relating to the Hartford Town Center, a mixed-use project incorporating buildings on Main Street, Market Street, Pratt Street, and Asylum Street (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Maps, 1998; Maps showing sites available for redevelopment (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Ebbets Field, 1998; Memo, newspaper clippings, map and proposal for building a replica of Ebbets Field in downtown Hartford (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Morgan Street Garage, 1999; Documents relating to design and construction of the garage including correspondence, memos, a draft contract, etc. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Morgan Street Garage, 1999; Plans, design schedule, project status report by CRKlewin, a Norwich construction firm (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Park Street, 2000; Draft of Park Street Revitalization Strategy (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Riverfront North, 2001; Brochure outlining plan for a parking complex with shuttle service (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Sheldon-Charter Oak, 1999; Survey produced by the Traffic and Parking Committee of the Coalition to Strengthen the Sheldon/Charter Oak Neighborhood (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Trinity College, 1998; Strategic plan, copies of emails (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - East Hartford, 2000; Photocopies of histories, historic preservation survey (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - East Hartford history, 2000; Correspondence, photocopies, map of old roads (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - East Hartford history, 2000; Photographs of Connecticut River waterfront and surrounding area (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - East Hartford maps, 2000; Photocopies of historic and modern maps of East Hartford (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - East Hartford-Rentschler Airport area, 2000; Transportation study and related photocopies relating to proposed improvements to East Hartford Boulevard, Silver Lane, Route 2 and Interstate 84 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - East Hartford-Rentschler Airport area, 2000; Rentschler Field Master Plan for development of former airport site including stadium, parking, and improved access (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - East Hartford - United Technologies Corporation, Pratt & Whitney Aircraft, 1983, 2000; Historic Resources Inventory of buildings and structures at Pratt & Whitney Aircraft and related newspaper clippings (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - East Hartford - United Technologies Corporation, Pratt & Whitney Aircraft, 1983, 2000; Brochures, newsletter (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - East Hartford - Burnside Avenue and Main Street plus, n.d., 1999; Brochures, newsletter (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Capital City Economic Development Authority, 2000; Facsimile communication with Patrick Pinnell (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Capital Region Council of Governments, 1998-2000; Annual reports, report on home sales prices, mission statement (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Commission on the City Plan, 1999; Downtown Development Plan and related documents (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Downtown Hartford Economic and Urban Design Action Strategy, 1998; Report prepared by Urban Strategies Inc. in association with Patrick Pinnell and others (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Hartford Downtown Council, 1999-2000; Meeting agenda, lists of priority actions and accomplishments, and newsletter (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Hartford Parking Authority, 2000; Drafts of policies and procedures for procurement and accounting (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Hartford Parking Authority, 1999; Applications for position of Executive Director (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Hartford Parking Authority, 2000; Proposal for a Comprehensively Managed Public Parking System (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Hartford Parking Authority, 2000-2001; By-laws, meeting agendas, correspondence (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - MetroHartford Millennium Project, 1997-1998; Action strategy, work force plan, final report, newspaper clipping (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Neighborhood Revitalization Plan, 1999; Request for qualifications for planning consultants (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Public Strategies Group, 1998; Vision statement for reinventing Hartford (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Saint Paul Design Center, 1999; Information on the Saint Paul Design Center, which worked with Patrick Pinnell on several Hartford projects (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Survey on Residential, Shopping, and Visitation in Downtown Hartford, 1998; Report prepared by Development Strategies for Urban Strategies, Inc. on behalf of the MetroHartford Millennium Project and others (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous, 1998-1999; Photocopies, newspaper clippings, correspondence, proposal for a national urban heritage park (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Hartford Downtown Circulation Project, 2000-2001; Community Advisory Group meetings, notices (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Hartford Downtown Circulation Project, 2000-2001; Business cards and contacts (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Hartford Downtown Circulation Project, 2000; Correspondence between Greater Hartford Transit District, Capitol Region Council of Governments (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Hartford Downtown Circulation Project, 1998; Downtown Parking Study prepared by Desman Associates (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Hartford Downtown Circulation Project, 1999-2001; Miscellaneous brochures, flyers, newsletters (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Hartford Downtown Circulation Project, 1999-2001; Federal Transit Administration "New Start" Grant (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Hartford Downtown Circulation Project, 2001; Draft Final Technical Report on Regional Transit Strategy (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Hartford Downtown Circulation Project, n.d.; Glossary of Transit Terminology (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Hartford West Major Investment Study, 1999; Report prepared by Wilbur Smith Associates for the Connecticut Department of Transportation (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Regional Transit Strategy, 2000; Record of public meetings (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Regional Approach Distributions, 1998; Map showing North Meadows Parking Facility, G. Fox Parking Facility (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - New Britain-Hartford Busway, 2000; First project newsletter,report on High Capital Cost Transit Alternatives and letter from U.S. Department of Transportation Federal Transit Administration (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper clippings, 2000; Copies of clippings regarding Downtown Circulation Project and Hartford-New Britain Busway, (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Pedestrian survey, 2000; Blank survey form for survey of pedestrian activity in downtown Hartford conducted for the Downtown Hartford Circulation Project (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Plan and Schedule, 2000?; Plan and schedule developed by Parsons Brinkerhoff for the Greater Hartford Transit District Downtown Circulation Study (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Planning Committee and Stakeholders Committee meetings, 1999-2000; Agendas, handouts, and minutes of meetings concerning the Regional Transit Strategy (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Public information workshop, 2000; Invitation, notice, handouts, and copy of PowerPoint presentation on the Downtown Circulation Project. A post-it note by Patrick Pinnell reads "NOT well-received." (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Regional Transit Strategy: Evaluation Measures, 2000?; Part of a PowerPoint presentation? (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Route 175/Route 5/15 Improvement Plan, 2000?; Brochure outlining improvements to Routes 175, Route 5 and Route 15 in Newington and Wethersfield (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Transportation Improvement Program (TIP) Amendment, 2000; List of statewide programs, projects, and funding (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Transportation Demand Management, 2000; Report issued by Parsons Brinkerhoff and other documents relating to Regional Transit Strategy (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, November-December 1997 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, January-February 1998 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, March-April 1998 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, May-June 1998 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, July-December 1998 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, January-June 1999 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, July-December 1999 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, December 1999 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, January-May 2000 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, June-December 2000 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, January-February 2001 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Clippings, September 28, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, October 20-October 21, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, November 30, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, December 2-December 5, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, December 6-December 9, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, December 4-December 18, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, December 21-December 24, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Clippings, December 24-January 7, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Clippings, January 10-January 15, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Clippings, January 16-January 23, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Clippings, January 24-January 29, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Clippings, January-February, 1998? (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Clippings, January 31-February 6, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Clippings, February 7-February 16, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Clippings, January 5-February 24, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Clippings, February 10-February 19, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Clippings, February 20-February 27, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Clippings, March 1-March 13, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Clippings, March 13-March 20, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Clippings, March 21-March 29, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Clippings, March 30-April 5, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Clippings, April 6-April 9, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Clippings, April 11-April 22, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Clippings, April 24-May 1, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Clippings, May 4-May 8, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Clippings, May 10-May 15, 1998 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, May 17-May 29, 1998 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, June-July 1998 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, July 1998 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, July-August 1998 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, July 13-July 24, 1998 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, July 27-August 2, 1998 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Clippings, August 1998 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Clippings, July 31-August 21, 1998 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Clippings, August 3-August 7, 1998 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Clippings, August 10-August 14, 1998 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Clippings, September 1998 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Clippings, October 1998 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Clippings, November 1998 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Clippings, December 1998 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Clippings, January 1999 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, February 1999 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, March 1999 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, April 1999 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, May 1999 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, June 1999 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, July 1999 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Clippings, August 1999 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Clippings, September 1999 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Clippings, October 1999 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Clippings, October 1999 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, November 1999 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, December 1999 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, January 2000 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, February 2000 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, March 2000 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, April 2000 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Clippings, May 2000 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Clippings, June 2000 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Clippings, July 2000 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Clippings, August 2000 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Clippings, September 2000 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Clippings, October 2000 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Regional Transit Strategy, 2001; Draft of report prepared by Parsons Brinkerhoff Quade & Douglas, Inc. with cover memo and executive summary (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Zoning, 1990; Reprint from Municipal Code of the City of Hartford (Box 11, Folder 2)